<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The cure of hurtfull cares and fears. By master Thomas Pierson late rector of Brompton-Brian, in the county of Hereford</title>
            <author>Pierson, Thomas, ca. 1570-1633.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09646</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19910</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111955</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847214</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847214</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12239</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09646)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12239)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1580:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The cure of hurtfull cares and fears. By master Thomas Pierson late rector of Brompton-Brian, in the county of Hereford</title>
                  <author>Pierson, Thomas, ca. 1570-1633.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 76, [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. B[adger] for P. Stephens, and C. Meridith, and are to be sold at their shop at the signe of the golden Lion in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1636.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Apparently issued with STC 12897.5.--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anxiety --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Suffering --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12239:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12239:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CVRE OF HVRTFVLL CARES AND FEARES.</p>
            <p>By Maſter THOMAS PIERSON late <hi>Rector</hi> of <hi>Brompton-Brian,</hi> in the COUNTY of HEREFORD.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R.B.</hi> for <hi>P. Stephens,</hi> and <hi>C. Meridith,</hi> and are to be ſold at their Shop at the ſigne of the <hi>golden Lion</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1636.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12239:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12239:2"/>
            <head>TO THE TRVLY NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE S<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Robert Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> Knight of the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable order of the <hi>Bath; the glory of holines in this life,</hi> and the happineſſe of glory <hi>in the life to come.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat I preſume to preſent this little Treatiſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, is not my reſpect
<pb facs="tcp:12239:3"/>
only but your right: your intereſt in all, the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> the <hi>Worke,</hi> and <hi>Publication,</hi> doth more then require it: For the Treatiſe it ſelfe, beſides the matter which is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, the art ſhewed in it, I conceive is ſuch as may bee exemplary. For the <hi>Author,</hi> as no man knew him better than your ſelfe, of whom I have heard you ſay, <hi>That you eſteemed your ſelfe much honoured, in preſenting him to the Rectory of Brompton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brian,
<pb facs="tcp:12239:3"/>
where he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued a burning and a ſhining light above twenty yeares toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> ſo no man can bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter testifie with me, that his name is as an oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment newly powred out, and all the houſe of God where he was knowne, is filled with the odour of it. The ſweetneſſe of his voice ſtill Ecchoes in the eares of many precious ſoules which hung upon his lippes, whilst with the wiſe Preacher hee taught the people knowledge, yea
<pb facs="tcp:12239:4"/>
gave good heed, and ſought to finde out acceptable words, and words of truth, ſound ſpeeches ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with ſalt, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring both delight and grace to the hearers. And like a wiſe and faithfull ſteward of the myſteries of God, he hath left behind him many written treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſo plentifully ſtored with ſuch ſpirituall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, that future ages would riſe up and call him bleſſed, if his own works ſhould ſtand forth to praiſe him in the gate.
<pb facs="tcp:12239:4"/>
Wherein as no man living hath more intereſt then your ſelfe, ſo I know no man more able by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to commend them to the Church of God for excellent. If this breake the way, no paines of mine ſhall bee wanting, if you pleaſe to bring any of the reſt out after it. In the meane time I ſhould have thought my ſelfe guilty in ſome kind of Sacriledge, if I had not given way to the publiſhing of this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the good, I truſt, of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which by experience
<pb facs="tcp:12239:5"/>
hath beene found already, not acceptable onely but profitable alſo unto ſome. So ſubmitting the rest of my thoughts and deſires in this buſineſſe unto Yours; I reſt as I am ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wayes obliged to be,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips in all obſervant duty un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feignedly devoted,</hi> Christopher Harvey.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:12239:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12239:6"/>
            <p>Perlegi hoc Opuſculum cai Titulus <hi>(The Cure of hurtfull Cares and Feares)</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nà cum Epiſtolâ dedicatoriâ, quae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent in toto paginas <hi>76.</hi> in quibus non reperio aliquid ſanae doctrinae aut bonis moribus contrarium, quo minùs cum utili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate publicâ imprimi queant: ſub eâ tamen conditione, ut, ſi non intra tres men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes typis mandentur, haec licentia ſit om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino irrita.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Gulielm Haywood. R. R. D. Arch. Cant. Capellan. Domeſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12239:6"/>
            <head>THE CVRE OF <hi>Hurtfull Cares and Feares.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Philippians 4.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Be carefull for nothing: but in every thing, by prayer and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, with thankeſgiving, let your requeſt be made known unto God. <hi>7.</hi> And the peace of God, which paſſeth all under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſhall keepe your hearts and minds through Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the nine firſt verſes of this Chapter,<note place="margin">The cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the Text.</note> the Apoſtle pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12239:7"/>
the practice of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry chriſtian duties: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſome bee generall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to all Chriſtians, <hi>verſe</hi> 1.4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9. Others bee ſpeciall duties belonging to ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Philippi, verſe</hi> 2, 3. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the generall duties are the words of my Text, preſcribing unto Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſuch behaviour, as beſt befitteth them in times of diſtreſſe, and in caſes of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty: urging them ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by the ſingular fruit that will come thereof. The behaviour it ſelfe is propounded in a double duty: Firſt, by way of prohibition, what wee muſt not doe: Secondly,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12239:7"/>
by way of precept, what we muſt do. The prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is againſt care: the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept is for the exerciſe of prayer with thankſgiving, <hi>verſe</hi> 6. The encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto both is from the aſſurance of Gods peace, which paſſeth all under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, to keep our hearts and minds, through <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> verſe 7.</p>
            <p>For the firſt,<note place="margin">The mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the words</note> bee care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for nothing. This prohibition may ſeeme ſtrange, and contrary to the will of God, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counteth the careleſſe and improvident worſe than infidels, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. and ſendeth ſuch lazy bodyes to the Ant or Piſmire, <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.6. as alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12239:8"/>
carefulnes, as wel about the matters of the ſoule, both for our ſelves, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11. <hi>what careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?</hi> and for others, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. the care of all Churches commeth on me dayly: as alſo for the things of this life, <hi>Prov.</hi> 27.23. Bee diligent to know the ſtate of thy flock: and ſet thy heart upon thy herds: which implieth a great care in looking well unto them as the good huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife looketh well to the wayes of her houſhold, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.27.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As the Apoſtle ſpeaking of ſorrow calleth ſome godly ſorrow and ſome worldly, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10. ſo may we truly ſay of <hi>care</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:12239:8"/>
ſome is godly, ſome world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The godly <hi>care</hi> is that whereby a Chriſtian ſets his mind upon the duty of his place, in ſober manner to uſe lawfull meanes, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified by prayer, for the fruition of bleſſings, and freedome from evills, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpirituall or corporall, leaving the iſſue and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe wholly to <hi>Gods</hi> good will and pleaſure. World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly care is that, whereby a man, beſide the uſe of meanes, doth perplexe his mind, about the iſſue and ſucceſſe of things, which he deſires or feares; and doth not rely upon the mercy or providence of God for the ſame as hee ought to doe. And this is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12239:9"/>
the care here forbidden by the Apoſtle, when he ſaith, Bee carefull for nothing, meaning, as worldlings be, who vexe themſelves, and perplex their minds, about the iſſue and ſucceſſe of things, which they ought to leave to GODS good pleaſure. In which prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition ſo conceived this point is plaine.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and confirmed.</note>The Child of GOD muſt not perplex his mind; nor vex his heart with worldly carking care in any thing whatſoever. When in a ſober and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified manner, a man hath uſed lawfull meanes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing unto him, for the fruition of bleſſings, or freedome from evils, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12239:9"/>
or ſpiritual, he muſt not buſy his mind, about the iſſue &amp; ſucces, but leave that wholly to the Lord. This duty our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour doth plainely teach his Diſciples, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.25. &amp;c. Take no thought for your life; what ye ſhall eate, or what ye ſhal drink; or for your body, what ye ſhall put on. And for their better obſervance and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, doth twice more in that Chapter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat the ſame charge <hi>ver.</hi> 31. and 34. Therefore take no thought, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 3.6. The good wife muſt not bee afraid with any amaſement.</p>
            <p>The reaſons of this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are ſtrong.<note place="margin">Three rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:12239:10"/>
               <note place="margin">1. World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly care is needleſſe to a child of God.</note>Firſt, every Child of GOD hath an heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father that careth for him: and ſo his owne worldly raking care is needleſſe, 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 5.7. Caſt all your care upon him, for he careth for you. This reaſon our bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi> urgeth ſtrongly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Diſciples: as well from Gods prouidence o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver baſer Creatures, the Fowles of the ayre and the Lilies of the field, and therefore they muſt not thinke he will neglect his Children that are far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Matthew</hi> 6.26, 28. As alſo from his ſpeciall notice of all their wants, <hi>verſe</hi> 32. and aſſured rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe to make ſupply
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12239:10"/>
thereto upon their ſober uſe of lawfull means, when they chiefely ſet their hearts on heavenly things, <hi>verſe</hi> 33.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly care is very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracefull to a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</note> worldly care is very diſgracefull to a Chriſtian: arguing either their ſhamefull ignorance of <hi>Gods</hi> providence, which indeed extends it ſelfe to the very haires of their head <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.30. Or elſe their great weakeneſſe, if not their totall want, of true faith in God through Chriſt, and ſo is plaine heatheniſh as CHRIST telleth his Diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 32. After all theſe things, food and rayment, doe the Gentiles ſeeke in a worldly manner; as not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12239:11"/>
knowing they have a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in heaven that careth for them. For they that reſt and rely upon GOD for any bleſſing that hee hath promiſed, will wait for it in the ſober and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified uſe of lawfull meanes, and goe no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Hee that believeth will not make haſt, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 28.16. but will ſtirre up his ſoule to wait on GOD as <hi>David</hi> doth, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 42.5, 11. he that is weary of this waiting ſhameth his beleeving: like to <hi>Ioram</hi> King of Iſrael, who in the time of famine ſaid, <hi>This evill is of the Lord, what ſhould I wait for the Lord any longer?</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6.33. as they are ſaid not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12239:11"/>
in God, that truſt not in his ſalvation, that is, that reſt not upon his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for their preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.22.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3. World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly care is a burden to the ſoule, exceeding hurtfull.</note> worldly care is a great burden unto the the ſoule, not only vaine and unprofitable, but alſo exceeding hurtfull. That it is a burthen <hi>David</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth when ſpeaking hereof he ſaith, Caſt thy burthen upon the LORD; that is, whatſoever thou art care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for and wouldeſt have given thee, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 55.22. That it is vaine and unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable he plainly ſheweth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127.1, 2. It is vaine for you to riſe early, to ſit up late, to eate the bread of ſorrowes (meaning
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12239:12"/>
through carking care) if the <hi>Lords</hi> bleſſing bee not with you.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Matthew</hi> 6.27. <hi>Which of you by taking thought can adde one cubite unto his ſtature?</hi> If ye then bee not able to doe that thing which is leaſt, why take yee thought for the reſt? <hi>Luke</hi> 12.25, 26. And that it is very hurtfull, the notation of the word uſed by the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> ſheweth plainely, impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a dividing, or parting the mind aſunder: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>quaſi</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. This carking care is the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous mans diſeaſe? They pierce themſelves through with many ſorrowes, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12239:12"/>
many times bring upon themſelves moſt heavy judgements. What elſe did move <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphyrah</hi> to diſſemble with the Apoſtle, and to lye unto GOD, about the price, for which they ſold their poſſeſſion, ſaying, they had brought all, when as indeed they kept back a part? Vndoubtedly, they were diſtruſtfully carefull about their future mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and proviſion: but it coſt them deere, even both their lives by ſudden death, <hi>Acts</hi> 5. <hi>verſe</hi> 1, 2, 3. &amp;c. And are not theſe worldly cares the chiefe of thoſe ſpirituall thornes, which choake the ſeed of grace in the ground
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12239:13"/>
of mens hearts, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it becomes unfruitfull? <hi>Matthew</hi> 13.22. and ſo neere unto curſing, whoſe end is to bee burned? <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.8.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p n="3">3. Vſes of the doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. True Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is the only way to true content.</p>
               </note>Now ſith whatſoever is written aforetime is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for our learning, <hi>Ro.</hi> 15.4. Let us make application hereof unto our ſelves. And firſt, would the Spirit of <hi>God</hi> have the hearts of his Children voyd of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cares? Then undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly the ſincere imbracing of true Religion is the only way to get true content and comfort in any eſtate: for what is or can be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to his ſoule, to whom the <hi>God</hi> of heaven ſaith be carefull for nothing? Hee
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12239:13"/>
ſpeaketh not this to al that have the ſhew of godlines, but to ſuch as have the power and truth thereof: <hi>For Gods kingdome is not in word, but in power,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.20. and in whom this power is, in them is, <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, peace, and joy in the Holy Ghoſt, Rom.</hi> 14.17. Even joy unſpeakable and glorious, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. ſuch as the world can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther give to its owne, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.27. nor take away from the godly, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.22.</p>
            <p>But me thinkes,<note place="margin">Two ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and anſwered. I. Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> I heare the men of the world call in queſtion the truth of this point, That true Religion ſhould afford ſuch ſweet content unto the ſoule.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12239:14"/>
The exerciſes thereof bee wearineſſe unto <hi>them, Mal.</hi> 1.13. therein <hi>they</hi> can meet with no ſuch thing.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſw.</note>I anſwer. This ſweet content and comfort in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is a fruit of GODS holy Spirit, <hi>Gala.</hi> 5.22. <hi>The fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace,</hi> &amp;c. which Spirit <hi>God gives to true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, Iohn</hi> 7.39. who turne from ſinne, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 1.23. and make conſcience of obedience, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.32. And therefore have the godly teſtified the fruition and feeling of it, as <hi>David Pſalm.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Thou haſt put gladneſſe in my heart, more than in the time that their corn &amp; their wine increaſed.</hi> Hee had more joy in Gods
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12239:14"/>
favour then <hi>worldlings</hi> had in all their abundance. <hi>God</hi> was his exceeding joy, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 43.4. his favour was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than life: and therwith his ſoule was ſatisfied as with marrow and fatneſſe, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 63.3, 5. Vnto <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy</hi> alſo was Gods word the joy and rejoycing of his heart, <hi>Ieremy</hi> 15.16. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> ſang prayſes to GOD in the priſon, when their feet were made faſt in the ſtocks, and they had beene ſore beaten and ſhamefully intreated the day before, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.23, 24, 25. They found by experience that GOD in Chriſt was the father of mercies and the God of all comfort who comforted
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12239:15"/>
them in all their tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: as the ſufferings of <hi>Chriſt</hi> did abound in them, ſo their conſolation alſo abounded by Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.3, 4, 5. But naturall men, that live in ſinne, doe want the ſpirit, <hi>Iude verſe</hi> 19. and therefore no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell though they have no ſavour nor relliſh of joy in Religion. The naturall man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of <hi>God,</hi> they are fooliſhneſſe unto him; neither can he know them becauſe they are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually diſcerned, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. They are ſtrangers from the covenants of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Epheſi.</hi> 2.12. and a ſtranger doth not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medle with this joy, <hi>Pro.</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:12239:15"/>
14.10. It is one of the myſteries of the kingdome which is not knowne by nature but by the gift of grace, <hi>Matthew</hi> 13.11. The <hi>Philiſtims</hi> could not read <hi>Sampſons</hi> riddle till they had plowed with his Heyfer, <hi>Iudges</hi> 14.18. No more can naturall men diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the ſweet content of grace but by the operation of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> the only worker of grace.</p>
            <p>But whence is it,<note place="margin">2. Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> ſaith the natural man, that ſome who are ſtrickt and zealous in Religion, and ſeeme to make great conſcience of their wayes, doe yet ſpend their dayes in much bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and ſorrow, giving ſmal evidence that any ſuch joy
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12239:16"/>
is to be found in their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Anſw.</note>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Surely God doth then viſit upon them the dayes of <hi>Baalim, Hoſ.</hi> 2.13. wherein they went after their owne ſinfull pleaſures and forgot the <hi>Lord:</hi> therefore doth the LORD write bitter things againſt them, and make them to poſſeſſe the ſinnes of their youth, <hi>Iob</hi> 13.26. Becauſe they have ſinned againſt the Lord, and have not obeyed the voice of the Lord, therefore is this evill happened unto them, <hi>Ieremy</hi> 44.23. But yet if this their ſorrow for their former ſinnes bee godly, which wil beſt appeare by the amendment of their
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12239:16"/>
lives, they ſhall finde by good experience, that of very faithfulneſſe God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted them: as <hi>David</hi> did <hi>Pſalme</hi> 119.75. <hi>For the</hi> LORD <hi>will not caſt off for ever; but though hee cauſe griefe yet will he have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion according to the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of his mercies, Lam.</hi> 3.31, 32. In duetime he will comfort all ſuch mourners, <hi>and give them beauty for aſhes, the oyle of joy for mourning, the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of praiſe for the ſpirit of heavineſſe, Iſaiah</hi> 61.2, 3. <hi>For to the upright there ariſeth light in darkeneſſe, that is, joy and gladneſſe in diſtreſſe, Pſalme</hi> 112.4. And though for a time they be in heavineſſe, yet
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12239:17"/>
peace ſhall come: <hi>They that wait upon the Lord, ſhall renew their ſtrength, Iſaiah</hi> 40.31. <hi>Many be the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the righteous, but the Lord will deliver them out of all, Pſal.</hi> 34.19.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Vſe for reproofe. Worldly care is unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of adoption.</note>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> this ſhewes plainly how unworthy of the Lord, and of their holy profeſſion of adoption, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that live in the boſome of the Church doe lead their lives. For what is more ordinary than to call God Father, in ſaying the <hi>Lords</hi> Prayer? And yet who can ſay my heart is cleane, I am free from theſe worldly carking cares? For though like bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſap it ſometime lye hid in the root of the heart, yet
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12239:17"/>
indeed hath it a daily ſpring time, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by theſe bad fruits which doe fearefully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in many mens lives.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Five evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of worldly care.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſes to get worldly wealth.</p>
               </note> manifold unjuſt and ungodly practiſes to get or encreaſe worldlie wealth, as falſe weights and meaſures, lying, ſwearing and forſwearing, extorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſtealing, oppreſſion, and the like. Where any of theſe are in uſe &amp; practice, plaine evidence is given of diſtruſt in GODS provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and ſo of the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of this ſinfull world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carking care. For were men indeed perſwaded that the power to get wealth came from God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8 18. and that his bleſſing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12239:18"/>
made them rich, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 10.22. they would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent themſelves with the moderate uſe of lawfull meanes to ſerve his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, wherein they might comfortably wait for his bleſſing; and not betake themſelves to ſuch ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly courſes, as are plaine ſervices of the Divell, the God of this world, for the wealth thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary uſe of wicked meanes to remove corporall evills.</note>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> the ordinary uſe of wicked and forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den meanes to prevent or remove worldly loſſes and corporall evils, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with Magicians, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or Sorcerers, as <hi>Saul</hi> did when he was diſtreſſed by the Hoaſt of the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtims,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.7. <hi>Seeke
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12239:18"/>
me a woman that hath a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar ſpirit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And Aha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziah King of Iſrael, who ſent to enquire of Baalzebub the God of Ekron, whether hee ſhould recover of his diſeaſe,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 1.1, 2. This is a moſt fearefull proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of diſtruſt in GOD, when they ſeeke to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell Gods utter enemy. <hi>Is it not becauſe there is no God in Iſrael, that thou ſendeſt to enquire of Baalzebub the God of Ekron? ver.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to ſanctifie the uſe of lawfull meanes by prayer.</note> the ordinary neglect to ſanctifie the uſe of lawful means by prayer to GOD for his bleſſing. Thus <hi>Aſa</hi> one of the good Kings of <hi>Iudah</hi> ſinned, <hi>when being diſeaſed in his feet he ſought unto the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12239:19"/>
and not unto the Lord,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.12. And it is the common courſe of many families, to follow their worldly buſines dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, but ſeldome or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to ſanctifie their labour and paines by prayer and thankſgiving to Almighty God the giver of all bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. Exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and feare in times of danger.</note>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> exceſſive ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and feare in times of danger and diſtreſſe, with great deadneſſe of heart when outward meanes do faile and dangers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach: as though the power and mercy of God for their helpe and ſafety were tyed to the meanes. <hi>This was the ſinne of Iſrael at the Red Sea: when the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12239:19"/>
Hoaſt of Pharaoh drew neere unto them they were ſore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayd, and cryed out againſt Moſes for bringing them out of Aegypt, Exodus</hi> 14.10, 11, 12. <hi>Hence alſo came all their murmurings in the wilderneſſe, when they wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted bread, or fleſh, or water,</hi> as <hi>Exodus</hi> 16.3. and 15, 24. They had not yet lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to reſt and rely upon his power and providence that brought them thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5. Frailties hearing of GODS Word.</note> fruitleſſe and unprofitable hearing of Gods word. <hi>For the cares of this world are one kind of ſpirituall thornes that choake the ſeed of grace in the ground of mens hearts, that it brings no fruit to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12239:20"/>
Luke</hi> 8. <hi>verſe</hi> 14.</p>
            <p>All theſe give plaine evidence of worldly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king care, &amp; juſtly deſerve reproofe for tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing this holy command, that bids us, <hi>Be carefull for nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. Vſe: for admoni i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon moſt needfull though hard to corrupt nature.</note> For admonition, it ſerves fitly to move every one, to endeavour obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to this command, in labouring to free his heart in every thing from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſtfull worldly care. A leſſon moſt needfull in theſe evill dayes and peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous times; hard indeed to our corrupt nature, which the Scripture calleth <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>bloud.</hi> But the child of GOD muſt looke to a better guide, and not plead
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12239:20"/>
for it, <hi>for fleſh and bloud cannot inherit the kingdome of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.50. <hi>The wiſdome of the fleſh is death: and ſo rebellious to the will of God, that they that are in the fleſh cannot pleaſe God, Rom.</hi> 8.6, 7, 8.</p>
            <p>Now the practiſe of this duty ſtands in this:<note place="margin">Wherein the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of this duty ſtands.</note> that uſing lawfull meanes moderately, for the fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of bleſſings, or free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from evils, we then ſanctifie the ſame by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to GOD for his mercy and bleſſing; and then leave the iſſue and ſucceſſe wholly to his good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, whatſoever the caſe be. Thus doing we ſhall neither tempt God by neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of meanes, nor yet
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12239:21"/>
perplex our ſelves about the ſucceſſe,<note place="margin">What ground we muſt lay that wee may do ſo.</note> through di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt in his mercy. And that wee may ſo doe, wee muſt lay this good founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Make ſure we ſtand rightly in covenant with GOD through faith in CHRIST IESUS: <hi>for hee that commeth unto God muſt beleeve, Hebrewes</hi> 11.6. and then we have good title to all Gods promiſes, whereat true faith doth ever looke: and to them that have obtained that pretious grace are given exceeding great and preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous promiſes, 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 1.1, 4. <hi>All the promiſes of God are in him, yea, and in him, Amen, that is, in Chriſt Ieſus moſt ſure and certaine
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12239:21"/>
to true beleevers,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. This eſtate once had we muſt in every thing that may perplex us ſtir up this pretious grace of faith, and ſet it a working: w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſeemes to be the <hi>Lords</hi> meaning in that golden ſentence oft repeated, <hi>The juſt ſhall live by faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">That faith may have its perfect worke three things to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</note> 
               <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.38. And that this grace may have its perfect worke, to free our hearts from diſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and perplexing world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cares, wee muſt rightly informe our ſelves in three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in Gods ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne right to inflict upon his deareſt ſervants, when, where, and how hee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth either death it ſelfe, or
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12239:22"/>
any evill that is a forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner thereof, for their ſinnes originall and actuall.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent nature of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and in his divine royalty, for time, meaſure, and manner of perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in Gods good pleaſure to exerciſe his Children and ſervants ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times under ſore afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: all of which he will cauſe to worke for their good, out of his tender love in <hi>Chriſt</hi> which remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth conſtant unto them, under their greateſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Gods right and ſoveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note>For the firſt: that God hath right and ſoveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to inflict upon his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12239:22"/>
ſervants, either death it ſelfe, or any evill that is a forerunner thereof, as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, ſickneſſe, ſword of the enemy and the like, when, and where he will, for their ſinnes originall and actuall, is moſt plaine, <hi>Romans</hi> 5.12. <hi>By one man ſinne entred into the world and death by ſin, and death went over all, in as much as all have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, Hebr.</hi> 9.27. <hi>It is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed unto man once to dye.</hi> Death then being our debt to God, who ſhall deny him liberty to call for his due. And for his right to inflict upon them hunger, thirſt, ſickneſſe, ſorrow and the like, none can deny it, that conſiders the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the godly: as of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12239:23"/>
               <hi>Iob in loſſe of goods, and of all his Children by ſudden death, Iob</hi> 1.15.16, 19. <hi>in grievous boyles upon his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, from the ſole of his foot unto his crowne,</hi> Chapter 2. ver. 7. and of <hi>David, who complaines that hee had no ſoundneſſe in his fleſh, Pſal.</hi> 38.3. <hi>his wounds ſtanke and were corrupt verſe</hi> 5. <hi>his loynes were filled with a loathſome diſeaſe verſe</hi> 7. <hi>he was feeble and ſore bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: yea hee roared for the very diſquietneſſe of his heart, verſe</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</note>For the ſecond: Gods promiſes are of two ſorts: <hi>ſome concerne the life that now is; others that which is to come,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. And among theſe latter, which
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12239:23"/>
be heavenly and ſpirituall there is a difference. Some are of bleſſings abſolutely neceſſary to ſalvation, as juſtification, adoption, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation and the like: others are very comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, but yet not ſimply neceſſary to ſalvation, as the ſenſible feeling of <hi>Gods</hi> love, and inward joy ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, ſtrength of faith and great increaſe in other gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, farre above that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which is ſimply need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the being and truth of grace. Now GODS promiſes of bleſſings ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply needful to ſalvation, be abſolutly made in <hi>Chriſt</hi> to true beleevers, without exception; as <hi>Acts</hi> 16.31. <hi>Beleeve in the Lord Ieſus
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12239:24"/>
and thou ſhalt bee ſaved.</hi> But other ſpirituall graces leſſe neceſſary, and all tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall bleſſings muſt bee underſtood to be promiſed with the exception of the Croſſe: to wit, that true beleevers ſhall have them upon their ſober and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified uſe of lawfull meanes, unleſſe it ſeeme good to GOD, by the want of ſuch bleſſings, to correct them for their ſins, as he did <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.10, 11. <hi>The ſword ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver depart from thy houſe, becauſe thou haſt deſpiſed me, Pſalme</hi> 118.18. <hi>The Lord hath chaſtened me ſore, but hee hath not given mee over unto death.</hi> Or elſe to make tryall of their faith
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12239:24"/>
and patience, <hi>as hee dealt with Iob in his afflictions, Iob</hi> 2.3. <hi>Thou moveſt mee againſt him to deſtroy him without cauſe:</hi> and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 23.10. <hi>He knoweth the way that I take: when hee hath tryed mee I ſhall come forth as gold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo Gods royalty for time, manner,<note place="margin">Gods roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty.</note> and meaſure of performing his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes is very remarkeable. In theſe circumſtances he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth and exerciſeth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine liberty, and looketh that his Children ſhould wait for the evidence of his good pleaſure, and reſt contented therewith when he doth manifeſt the ſame, though it doe not anſwer their deſires. And he bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:12239:25"/>
thoſe, that will limit or confine him in any of theſe, <hi>as his people did in the wilderneſſe, when they would as it were point out their own proviſion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">For time.</note> 
               <hi>Pſalme</hi> 78.20, 41. In particular, for the time, when GOD will do this or that thing, which hee hath promiſed indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely, he ſhewes his royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to his Diſciples, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.7. <hi>It is not for you to know the times, which God hath put in his owne power.</hi> In this circumſtance he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth <hi>the patience of faith,</hi> ſaying,<note place="margin">Manner.</note> 
               <hi>Hee that beleeveth ſhall not make haſt, Iſa.</hi> 28.15. And for manner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance ſometime he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the particular bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing asked: <hi>As upon Elias
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12239:25"/>
prayer he ſent firſt drought, and then after rayne, Iames</hi> 5.17, 18.</p>
            <p>Other while inſtead of the bleſſing asked, hee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth ſome other thing an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable thereunto, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king more for his owne glory and the good of his ſervants: <hi>as when Paul be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought the Lord thrice, that the thorne in the fleſh, the meſſenger of Satan might depart from him, God ſaid, my grace is ſufficient,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7, 8, 9.</p>
            <p>GOD did not free him from the aſſault, but gave him ability of grace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt. Yea our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in his bitter agony in the Garden, offered up prayers and ſupplications,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12239:26"/>
with ſtrong crying and teares, unto him that was able to ſave him from death, and was heard in that he feared, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 5.7. Not by a totall freedome from the Cuppe of his bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter paſſion, though he had ſaid, <hi>Father, if it be poſsible let this Cuppe paſſe from me, Matthew</hi> 26.39. but by making him willing and able to beare it, and in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering to overcome. For after this prayer he ſaid to <hi>Peter, The Cuppe which my Father hath given mee, ſhall I not drink it? Iohn</hi> 18.11. <hi>and in ſuffering bee over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came,</hi>
               <note place="margin">And mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming his promiſes.</note> 
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the meaſure of his gifts and bleſſings to his ſervants, and of their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12239:26"/>
from evills, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth and exerciſeth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine liberty and ſoveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>Some he maketh high, others low: ſome rich, and others poore, Iob</hi> 34.19 <hi>To one he giveth five talents, to another two, to another one, Matthew</hi> 25.15. <hi>He ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered no man to doe wrong to Abraham, Iſaac, and Iacob, but rebuked Kings for their ſakes, Pſalm.</hi> 105.14. <hi>Yet he will ſuffer Ioſeph to be ſold for a ſervant, and to be layd in irons wrongfully, verſe</hi> 17, 18. and hee ſuffers his ſervant <hi>Iob</hi> to be robbed of his goods, bereaved of his Children, ſore afflicted in his body, and grieved by his deareſt friends, ſo as he eſcaped, but with the Skin
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12239:27"/>
of his teeth, <hi>Iob</hi> 19. <hi>verſe</hi> 19, 20.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p n="3">3. Gods good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe his Children in afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for their good foure wayes.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. To purge out ſome cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</p>
               </note>For the third, it pleaſeth God many times to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe his deere children un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſore afflictions, for his glory in their good ſundry wayes; as Firſt, to purge out ſome corruption, and to make them white, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.35. <hi>Some of them of underſtanding ſhall, fall to try them, and to purge, and to make them white, Iob</hi> 23.10. <hi>When hee hath tryed mee I ſhall come forth as the gold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. To teach them obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</note>Secondly, to teach them obedience, as well in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchewing evill, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.67. <hi>Before I was afflicted I went aſtray: but now have I kept thy word:</hi> as alſo in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12239:27"/>
doing good, ſo <hi>Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus learned obedience by the things he did ſuffer, Heb.</hi> 5.8. <hi>and the Apoſtles learned by afflictions to truſt in God,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.9.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3. To try their faith and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> to try their faith and patience, as hee did in <hi>Iob: whence great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions are called fierie try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls ſent to try Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4 12. as <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.36, 37. <hi>Others alſo were tryed by cruell mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and ſcourgings, yea by bonds and impriſonments: they were ſtoned, ſawen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder, tempted, ſlaine with the ſword,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">4. To fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them in holines and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> for their fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance in grace and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe here, and in joy and happineſſe hereafter, <hi>Iames</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:12239:28"/>
1.3. <hi>The tryall of faith worketh patience, Hebr.</hi> 12.10. <hi>God doth chaſten us for our profit, that we might bee partakers of his holineſſe, verſe</hi> 11. <hi>though it bee not joyous for the preſent, yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it yeeldeth the quiet fruit of righteouſneſſe.</hi> Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is Gods Schoole wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he teacheth the ſoules of his Children many a ſweet leſſon, as <hi>Pſalme</hi> 119.71. <hi>It is good for me that I have beene afflicted that I might learne thy ſtatutes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This brings down their hearts, and cauſeth them to be more frequent in hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and earneſt prayer, and more carefull to meditate on Gods word and works, as <hi>Pſalme</hi> 77.2. <hi>In the day
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:12239:28"/>
of my trouble I ſought the Lord, verſe</hi> 3. <hi>I remembred God: I complained, I conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the dayes of old,</hi> &amp;c. all which are notable means of growth in grace, whereby, no doubt, their preſent joy &amp; future glory ſhall bee much increaſed: for our light affliction, which is but for a moment, worketh for us a far more exceeding and eternall weight of glory, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. <hi>The tryall of faith ſhall be found unto praiſe, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and glory at the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7. <hi>If wee ſuffer we ſhall alſo raigne with him,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. All which are great benefits of afflictions, and may well perſwade us, that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12239:29"/>
in the very extremity of them Gods love in Chriſt is conſtant towards us. <hi>For what ſhall ſeparate us from the love of Chriſt? Shall tribulation, or diſtreſſe, or perſecution, or famine, or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, or perill, or ſword,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Nay in all theſe things we are more than conquerers, through him that loved us. For I am perſwaded, that neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creature ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord, Rom.</hi> 8.35.37, 38.39. <hi>God correcteth every ſon whom he receiveth, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12239:29"/>
therein offereth himſelfe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, as to ſonnes, Hebr.</hi> 12.6, 7.</p>
            <p>Theſe things well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood and thought upon will much enable faith to quiet and ſtay the heart in any diſtreſſe whatſoever.<note place="margin">Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the doctrine in a caſe of ſpirituall diſtreſſe through feare of damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> For, to beginne with the greateſt matter of all, ſay thy ſoule is perplexed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thy ſalvation, thou haſt great feares of hell, and little hopes of heaven, what muſt thou now doe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, look thou ſtand rightly in covenant with God, through faith in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> in whom hee revealeth himſelfe to bee the God of grace and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, juſtifying the ungodly and ſaving ſinners, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12239:30"/>
in the <hi>Lord Ieſus.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, whether thou uſe the means ordained to this end. Now Gods meanes for this bleſſing is to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in the Lord Ieſus, Acts</hi> 16.31. <hi>Beleeve in the Lord Ieſus Chriſt and thou ſhalt be ſaved, Iohn</hi> 3.16. <hi>God ſo loved the world that he gave his only begotten Sonne, that whoſoever beleeveth in him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life.</hi>
               <note place="margin">What it is to believe.</note> Now thus to beleeve is to reſt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon that which <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> as Redeemer and Mediator hath done and ſuffered for the ſalvation of his Church. Aske then thine owne heart, whether thou bee not perſwaded, that which God in <hi>Christ
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12239:30"/>
Ieſus</hi> is plentifull redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſalvation, and in none other? demand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, whether thou doe not unfeignedly deſire to be found of God in Chriſt, and to reſt and rely upon that, which hee hath done and ſuffered for thy juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and ſalvation? Then conſider, whether thou doe uſe Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances conſcionably, and in an holy manner, to get this grace of faith, and to grow therein. Gods Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, we know,<note place="margin">GODS means for faith, the Word and Prayer.</note> are the word and prayer: <hi>for faith commeth by hearing the word of God preached, Rom.</hi> 10.14, 17. <hi>and prayer obtaines the</hi> HOLY GHOST, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13. <hi>Which is the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12239:31"/>
ſpirit of faith,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13. therefore did the Diſciples by prayer ſeeke faith at Chriſts hands, ſaying; <hi>Lord increaſe our faith,</hi> or put faith into us,<note place="margin">The holy manner of uſing the meanes of faith in 3. things. 1. Breaking of the courſe of every knowne ſinne.</note> 
               <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.5. The conſcionable and holy manner of uſing the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Ordinances ſtands in three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, breaking off the courſe of every knowne ſinne, which is a worke of darkeneſſe; wherein wee cannot live and have fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with Chriſt, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.6. Therefore <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaih, <hi>Turne you at my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. Lo, I will powre out my ſpirit upon you, Proverbs</hi> 1.23. and <hi>Iohn Baptiſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared the way of the Lord by preaching repentance unto
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12239:31"/>
the people, Matth.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3. without which there is lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle hope of attayning true faith in <hi>Chriſt, Mat.</hi> 21.32.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. Hartily deſiring the grace we ſeeke for.</note> we muſt truly and hartily deſire the grace we ſeeke for. This deſire is ſpirituall hunger and thirſt whereto God hath made a promiſe of ſatisfaction, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 44.3. <hi>I will powre water upon him that is thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and flouds upon the dry ground: I will powre my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit upon thy ſeed, Mat.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Bleſſed are they that hunger and thirſt after righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for they ſhall bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3. Yeelding conſciona<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to that wee know.</note> we muſt yeeld concionable obedience to that we know, as well in eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewing evill as in doing
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:12239:32"/>
good: for to ſuch belongs the gift of the <hi>Holy Ghost, Acts</hi> 5.32. <hi>Wee are wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and the Holy Ghost, which</hi> GOD <hi>gives to them that obey him.</hi> Thus every one that would bee ſaved muſt bee carefull to doe. And when we have ſo done <hi>we muſt cast our burthen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord, Pſalme</hi> 55.22. that is, reſt and rely upon the LORD for that thing, which wee ſo ſeeke for, in the foreſaid uſe of meanes: and then have we his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe for the obtaining thereof; for he hath ſaid, <hi>Commit thy way unto the Lord, trust in him, and hee ſhall bring it to paſſe, Pſalm.</hi> 37.5. On which promiſe if wee reſt, and wait pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:12239:32"/>
wee ſhall bee ſure to ſpeed: for hee hath ſaid, <hi>I will never leave thee nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake thee, Heb.</hi> 13.5. What though wee yet feele not the joy of his ſalvation, whereto <hi>David</hi> deſired to be reſtored? <hi>Pſalme</hi> 51.12. Yet if wee wait upon God in the uſe of meanes, wee may ſay to our ſelves as <hi>David</hi> did, <hi>Why art thou caſt downe, ô my ſoule? why art thou diſquieted in me? hope thou in God, for I ſhall yet praiſe him, who is the health of my countenance, and my God, Pſalme</hi> 42.11. When <hi>Abraham</hi> beleeved God, ſo as it was imputed to him for righteouſneſſe, hee had in himſelfe no ſenſe or feeling of any thing, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12239:33"/>
to ground his hope of that bleſſing which GOD promiſed: but only look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at God, being fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that hee who had promiſed was able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it, <hi>Romans</hi> 4.18, 19, 20, 21, 22. And on this practice of <hi>Abraham</hi> muſt we caſt our thoughts, when wee our ſelves are perplexed with doubting in our ſelves about our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: ſo ſhall wee give glory to God, and receive his gift of eternall life, promiſed to all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve: As <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Sarah</hi> gave glory to God, in beleeving his promiſe, and received a ſonne, when they were paſt age, in themſelves hopeleſſe <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.11.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:12239:33"/>Againe,<note place="margin">Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the doctrine in caſes of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe with out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward evils</note> ſay thou be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed with outward evills, as warres, famine, ſickneſſe, baniſhment po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, impriſonment or the like: Nay, ſay that many of theſe come together up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee, ſo as thou art preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed out of meaſure above ſtrength, and in thine owne thinking thy caſe is deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, muſt thou not be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full now? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Surely no further than to uſe law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meanes for thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and deliverance, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying the ſame by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to God for his bleſſing thereupon: which when thou haſt done, though thy miſery bee with much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, yet if thou haſt faith, and canſt ſet it a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:12239:34"/>
thou ſhalt undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly, by ſome of the three forenamed conſiderations, much quiet thy ſelfe, and free thy ſoule from exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive feare of evill.</p>
            <p>For firſt, doth this trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thee, that thou art ſo ſore diſtreſſed with ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, poverty, want, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, or the like? Here then call to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance GODS right to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict upon thee any, or all of theſe evills, when and where, and in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner he pleaſeth. For if thou bee a true beleever, thou wilt not think thy ſelfe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from any of thoſe evils, which the Scripture ſaith be incident to Gods children. It is the thought
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:12239:34"/>
of the wicked to ſay to himſelfe, I ſhall not be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: <hi>I ſhall never be in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, Pſalme</hi> 10.6. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſometime corruption remaining will ſuggeſt the like into the godly: hence <hi>David</hi> ſaid in his proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>I ſhall never bee moved;</hi> but GOD quickly taught him another leſſon, <hi>Thou didst hide thy face, and I was troubled, Pſalme</hi> 30.6, 7. and though godly <hi>Iob</hi> ſaid in the dayes of his honour and proſperity, <hi>I ſhall dye in my nest: I ſhall multiply my dayes as the ſand, Iob</hi> 29.18. Yet it ſeemes he had many times thoughts of his changeable eſtate; for ſaith hee, when his ſore af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affliction was upon him,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12239:35"/>
               <hi>The thing which I greatly feared is come upon me, Iob</hi> 3.25. And no doubt, if true faith be called to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell in the dayes of peace, it will ſay it is the Lords mercies thou art not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded: <hi>the continuance of thy freedome is the fruit of his patience:</hi> thou art debtor unto GOD for the ſuffering of any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward evill, yea and of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inward feares, either for correction of ſinne, or try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of grace, whenſoever he is pleaſed to call thee to it: Now ſhall the debtor thinke it ſtrange, that his creditor doth demand his due? Here the thiefe upon the Croſſe that repented will ſhame thee for repy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:12239:35"/>
though thou ſhouldſt ſuffer a ſhameful and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full violent death: feareſt thou not God, ſaith he to his fellow, ſeeing thou art in the ſame condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (meaning with <hi>Christ Ieſus</hi>) wee receive the due reward of our deeds: <hi>but this man hath done nothing amiſſe; Luke</hi> 23.40, 41. <hi>Looke therefore unto Ieſus the Author and finiſher of thy faith, who endured the Croſſe, and deſpiſed the ſhame, Hebrewes</hi> 12.2. <hi>He was led as a ſheepe to the ſlaughter, and as a Lambe before the ſheerer, dumb, ſo opened he not his mouth, Acts</hi> 8.32. <hi>And hereunto we are called, that is to ſuffer affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions patiently, becauſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:12239:36"/>
Chriſt alſo ſuffered for us, leaving us an example, that we ſhould follow his ſteppes,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21, 22, 23. But here thou thinkeſt upon GODS promiſe of delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance made to his ſervants that call upon him in the day of trouble, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 50.15. and becauſe thou haſt prayed and art not delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, therefore thou doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of his favour, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.1, 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here then, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſecond thing before commended to our conſideration, call to remembrance the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent nature of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and the exception of the Croſſe to bee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in all promiſes of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:12239:36"/>
bleſſings temporall, and ſpirituall alſo, which are not ſimply neceſſary to ſalvation. Let thy heart alſo think upon Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative royall for time meaſure and manner, of performing theſe promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: and know that if God have given thee faith and patience in afflictions, though they bee great and of long continuance, yet he hath vouchſafed graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous audience to thy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: even the ſame that he did to our bleſſed Saviour in the time of his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as before is ſhewed.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, when thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe and griefe is very great, is thine heart affraid of <hi>Gods</hi> forſaking of thee?
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:12239:37"/>
and canſt thou hardly think he will ſuffer it to goe ſo ill with thoſe that bee his Children, as it doth with thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Yet bee not diſmaid: it is no marvell to ſee the weake reeds ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with thoſe blaſts which make the ſtrong ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dars to bow and bend. When <hi>Ionas</hi> the Prophet was in the Whales belly, hee ſaith to GOD, <hi>I am cast out of thy ſight, Ionas</hi> 2.4. Nay, our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour himſelfe cryed out upon the Croſſe, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken me, Matthew</hi> 27.46. know therefore thou that makeſt conſcience of thy wayes, that this feare of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:12239:37"/>
Gods forſaking thee, in times of diſtreſſe, is from humane frailty, which the beſt have in them while they bee in this world, and will more ſtrongly aſſault them, upon the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of former ſinnes, though repented of, and upon the conſcience of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption remaining, though it doe not raigne: as wee may ſee in <hi>Iob</hi> when he ſaith unto God, <hi>wherefore hideſt thou thy face, and holdeſt mee for thine enemy? For thou writeſt bitter things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, and makeſt mee to poſſeſſe the iniquities of my youth, Iob</hi> 13.24, 26. and more fully in <hi>David</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging his frailty in this very caſe; <hi>My ſpirit,</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:12239:38"/>
ſaith he, <hi>was overwhelmed, I am ſo ſore troubled, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſpeake. Will the Lord caſt off for ever? Is his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy cleane gone? Hath God forgotten to be gracious? And I ſaid, this is mine ininfirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that is, this is my great weakeneſſe to doubt of Gods mercy, becauſe of my pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent troubles, Pſalme</hi> 77.3.4, 7, 8, 9, 10.</p>
            <p>Here thou muſt bring thy heart to the third thing before, commended to thy obſervation, <hi>viz.</hi> That GOD is pleaſed to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe his own deare children under great and ſore affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, for moſt excellent ends, as before is ſhewed. And indeed, what diſtreſſe can befall thee, wherein
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:12239:38"/>
faith, ſet a worke to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Gods dealing with his own children, may not ſet before thy view ſome of the Lords worthies, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than thy ſelfe, who have ſuffered the like or far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter evills then are upon thee? <hi>Was not righteous Lot taken captive in Warre, with all his goods? Gen.</hi> 14.12, 14 <hi>Was not Ioſeph ſold for a ſervant, caſt into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and layd in irons? Pſa.</hi> 105.17, 18. <hi>Was not the Prophet Ieremy ſmitten, and caſt into the myrie dungeon? Ier.</hi> 37.15, 16. <hi>Was not David hunted after to bee ſlaine by Saul, as one hunteth a Patridge in the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines?</hi> 1 <hi>Samuel</hi> 26.20. <hi>Was not Ziklag, where Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:12239:39"/>
and his men dwelt, burnt with fire by the <hi>Ama lakites</hi> and their wives, and Children with all their goods taken captives, 1 <hi>Sa.</hi> 30.1, 2, 5. Were not the Lords Prieſts, to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of foureſcore and five perſons, their City, both men, Women, and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and ſucklings, Oxen, Sheepe, and Aſſes ſmitten with the edge of the ſword by the command of their owne King, upon a falſe ſurmiſe of conſpiracy with innocent <hi>David?</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.13, 18, 19. Was not <hi>Ionathan, Davids</hi> deareſt friend, ſlaine by the uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed <hi>Philiſtims?</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 31.2. <hi>Nay was not good King Ioſiah ſlaine by Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh-Neco
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:12239:39"/>
at Megiddo like unto whom there was no KING before him, that turned to the Lord with all his heart, with all his ſoule,</hi> &amp;c. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 23.25, 27. Was not <hi>Iohn Baptist,</hi> grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than whom there roſe none before him among them that are borne of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <hi>Matthew</hi> 11.11. im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned by <hi>Herod,</hi> for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his duty, in telling him it was not lawfull for him to have his brother <hi>Philips</hi> Wife: and afterward be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed upon a moſt trivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all occaſion, even to grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie a damſell for her dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing? <hi>Mar.</hi> 6.18.26, 27. Which of the Prophets did not the people of the Iewes perſecute? <hi>Acts</hi> 7.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:12239:40"/>
52. Had not other of <hi>Gods</hi> ſervants, before Chriſts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, triall of cruell mockings and ſcourgings, of bonds and impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? Were they not ſtoned, ſawen aſunder, tempted, ſlaine with the ſword: did they not wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der about in Sheep-skins, and Goat-skinnes, being deſtitute, afflicted, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, though the world were not worthy of them? <hi>Hebrewes</hi> 11.36, 37, 38. And were not Chriſts own Diſciples, and holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſent forth as Lambes amongſt Wolves? <hi>Luke</hi> 10.3. and ſet forth as men approved unto death, made a ſpectacle to the world, reviled, perſecuted, defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:12239:40"/>
made the filth of the world, and the of-ſcouring of all things? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.9, 13. <hi>Was not Paul in labours abundant, in ſtripes above meaſure, in priſon frequent, in death oft? Received hee not of the Iewes five times forty ſtripes ſave one? was hee not thrice beaten with rods? once ſtoned? and thrice ſuffered ſhipwracke? was he not in journyings of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, in perills of waters, in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rills of robbers, in perills by his owne country men, in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rills by the heathen, in perills in the City, in perills in the wilderneſſe, in perills in the Sea, in perills among falſe brethren: in wearineſſe and painefulneſſe; in watchings often, in hunger and thirst,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:12239:41"/>
in faſtings often, in cold and nakedneſſe?</hi> &amp;c. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23, 24, 27. Nay, which is more than all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, was not our bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelfe perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and apprehended by the hands of the ungodly? <hi>Was he not buffeted and ſpit upon, crowned with thornes, ſcourged, and moſt ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemned and crucified?</hi> Now then, what thinkeſt thou of thy ſelfe? art thou better than theſe? doſt thou thinke God forſooke them in their afflictions? Why then, ſtirre up thy heart to ſay unto the Lord, with ſubjection to his will, even for the ſuſtaining of death it ſelfe; <hi>It is enough, Lord, take away my life, for I
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:12239:41"/>
am no better then my fathers,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.4.</p>
            <p>When affliction increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and death approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, then look unto <hi>Ieſus</hi> the Author and finiſher of thy faith leſt thou be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed and faint in thy mind. He left himſelfe an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that we ſhould follow his ſteps, in ſuffering af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction patiently. Now when <hi>Peter</hi> would have reſcued his apprehenſion by force of armes, he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bade him, ſaying, <hi>The Cup which my Father hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me, ſhall I not drink it? Iohn</hi> 18.11. And remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber this word of his, <hi>The ſervant is not greater than his maſter: If they have perſecuted mee, they will al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:12239:42"/>
perſecute you, Iohn</hi> 16. <hi>ver.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p>Adde hereunto the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of Gods ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all providence over thee in all thine afflictions: whereupon <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> bids thee, not to feare them that can kill the body, but are not able to kill the ſoule. <hi>Are not two Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes ſold for a farthing? and one of them ſhall not fall to the ground without your Father. The very haires of your head are all numbred. Feare ye not therefore, for yee are of more valew then many Sparrowes, Matthew</hi> 10.29.30, 31. <hi>God is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full who will not ſuffer you to bee tempted above that you are able, but will with the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:12239:42"/>
temptation alſo make a way to eſcape, that ye may be able to beare it,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, remember that his love in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> is firme and conſtant unto thee, in thy greateſt afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; See <hi>Romans</hi> 8.35, 38, 39. <hi>What ſhall ſeperate us from the love of God which is in Chriſt Ieſus?</hi> Surely nothing can doe it, as the things there named, and accounted unable, doe plainely ſhew, <hi>tribulation, anguiſh, or distreſſe, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, famine, perill, ſword,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For whom hee loves in</hi> CHRIST <hi>his Son, he loves to the end, Iohn</hi> 13.1. <hi>his gifts and calling to grace and favour in</hi> CHRIST <hi>are without repentance, Rom.</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:12239:43"/>
11.29. <hi>Nay more, rest aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that as the ſufferings of this preſent time are not worthy to bee compared with the glory that ſhall be revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in us, Rom.</hi> 8.18. <hi>ſo our light affliction, which is but for a moment, worketh for us a farre more excellent, and eternall weight of glory,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the whole</note>By theſe and ſuch like conſiderations will the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the godly ſuſtaine their infirmities. Thus will true beleevers, with godly <hi>David, encourage them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the Lord their God,</hi> even when violent death approcheth towards them, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.6. <hi>In the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of their owne perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoughts within them,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:12239:43"/>
will the Lords comforts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light their ſoules, Pſal.</hi> 94.19. Take notice therefore of this duty to ſtrive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt diſtracting world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cares. Conſider the grounds, or reaſons, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is preſſed: as that thine heavenly father ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for thee: theſe world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cares diſcredit and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace thine holy profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; they are a great and needleſſe, nay a very hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full burthen to thy poore ſoule: for the avoyding wherof thou muſt ſet faith a worke in every difficulty, ſmall or great, according to the direction before pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed. So though thou bee weake in thy ſelfe, yet ſhalt thou be ſtrong in the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:12239:44"/>
Lord, <hi>and in whatſoever ſtate thou art, thou ſhalt bee therewith content. Thou ſhalt know how to be abaſed, and how to abound; both to bee full and to be hungry; both to abound and to ſuffer need: yea, to doe all things through Chriſt which ſtrengtheneth thee, Phil.</hi> 4.11, 12, 13.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="request">
            <pb facs="tcp:12239:44"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12239:45"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12239:45"/>
            <head>A REQVEST <hi>By the Executors of</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Pierſon,</hi> occaſioned by the concealing and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of ſome of his</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and papers, by ſuch as <hi>borrowed them in the</hi> life time of Maſter <hi>PIERSON.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Heras in the former epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of ſome other wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings
<pb facs="tcp:12239:46"/>
of this reverend Author fit to be publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, I thinke it not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe to let the Reader underſtand, that the thing chiefely intended therein, is an excellent Expoſition of the firſt Epiſtle of Saint <hi>Iohn:</hi> a work, as is conceived both of extraordinary worth and uſe, and which ſhould have firſt bin offered to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like view, but that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on peruſall there was found a great breach in it, by reaſon that the
<pb facs="tcp:12239:46"/>
whole third Chapter, and a few verſes in the beginning of the fourth were wanting: that part being, as others had been, imparted to ſome private friend who hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto hath neither made reſtitution, nor given any notice of it. Wherupon it is thought fit by thoſe that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted in the whole, that this opportunity ſhould be taken to give notice of the defect in that part, being fully perſwaded that none
<pb facs="tcp:12239:47"/>
will either be ſo envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous at others, or deale ſo unfaithfully with him whoſe life and labours were wholly devoted to the publike good, as privately to detaine the papers themſelves, or any knowledge that they have of them, or their probable conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture to whom they have heard any of his writings have bin lent: when as by giving no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of that part they ſhal not only deale juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with thoſe whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:12239:47"/>
right it is, but wiſely likewiſe for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; who by that meanes in ſtead of a broken part may come to have the whole in ſuch ſort as will be fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter both for their own and others uſe, and withall prevent that imputation which wil lye upon them, if it be diſcovered otherwiſe; which they may eaſily conceive is neither im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible nor improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. For charity bids me hope that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealement
<pb facs="tcp:12239:48"/>
of it hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hath only beene out of ignorance in what hand the reſt did lye unto which it ought to be reſtored: and that ſince it is thus publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly now called for, it wil be no longer detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I will not ſay, from them that are particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly intereſted only; but from the Church of God in generall, and all good Chriſtians that might reap benefit and comfort by it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12239:48"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
